Columbia County Typographical Union, No. 896; Records apap013
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Columbia County Typographical Union No. 896 Records
1927, 1936-1968
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Typographical Union No. 896
apap013
0.66 cubic ft.
The Columbia County Typographical Union No. 896 records document the workings of this union from 1927-1968.
Access
Access to this record group is unrestricted.
Acquisition Information
All items in this manuscript group were donated to the University Libraries, M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives, by the Columbia County Typographical Union No. 896 on March 6, 1990.
Administrative History
The earliest typographical union in Hudson, N.Y., was the Hudson Typographical Union No. 531, chartered in 1902. That union is likely to have folded during the eight hour strike of 1906. During the 1920's, printers in Hudson had become acquainted with vacationing printers who were members of Albany Typographical Union No. 4. With support from the members of No. 4, the Hudson printers were chartered as the Hudson Typographical Union No. 896 in 1925. Unfortunately, the Great Depression arrived four years later, and the printers of No. 896 wanted to gain recognition as a bargaining agent. The International Typographical Union (ITU) refused to allow the Hudson printers to go forward with this action during a time of such financial havoc, and the members of No. 896 voted to surrender the charter, according to the Empire State Typographical Conference, Program, 1961.
In 1936, William A. Weinlein, an international representative of the ITU and former president of Albany Typographical Union No. 4, began re-organization of the Hudson local. By the end of that year, the local was re-chartered as Columbia County Typographical Union No. 896. The union at first had trouble winning contracts in Hudson. In 1937, No. 896 struck one publication after having little luck winning a contract, and was locked out of another after refusing to set copy for the struck publication. The strike and lockout were over after 11 days. The local slowly increased its numbers, adding shops in Chatham and Catskill in the 1950's, according to Ibid.
By the early 1960's, the local had begun to experience difficulties in administering a small union that had to fulfill the requirements of numerous labor laws and the regulations of the ITU itself. Recognizing the difficulties encountered by smaller unions, the ITU had been recommending that such unions seek to consolidate their forces with other locals. Younger members of No. 896 were, unfortunately, not anxious to take on the duties of officers, so in 1963 the local voted unanimously to begin negotiations to merge with Albany Typographical Union No. 4., according to Letter, Edward T. Thompson (secretary of Columbia County Typographical Union No. 896) to Albany Typographical Union No. 4. After three years of negotiations and planning, the Columbia County Typographical Union No. 896 surrendered its charter and merged into Albany Typographical Union No. 4 in October 1966, according to Letter, Edward T. Thompson (former secretary of Columbia County Typographical Union No. 896) to the Upper Hudson Area Central Labor Union Council, AFL-CIO, Nov. 28, 1966.
Scope and Contents
The records of Columbia County Typographical Union No. 896 offer complete documentation of the workings of this union since 1936. Only a single item (a program from 1927 of the local's first annual banquet) exists from its years as Hudson Typographical Union No. 896. The minutes (1936-66) and contracts (1937-66) are complete. There is substantial correspondence (1941, 1948-50, 1955-56, 1959-67) as well, most of which is organized by subject. The records of No. 896 represent a good source for studying the operation of a small union.
For related records, see the records of Albany Typographical Union No. 4 (APAP-007), into which the Columbia County Typographical Union (APAP-013) merged in 1966. For other labor union records relating to Columbia County, New York, see the records of the Hudson Valley Area Joint Board of the Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union (APAP-050); and the records of the International Union of Electronic, Electrical, Technical, Salaried and Machine Workers (IUE), Local 379, Match Workers' Union (APAP-024). For additional labor collections in the Department, see the online Labor subject guide.
Reproductions of items from this collection are available in the exhibit Documenting Labor Inside and Out: Labor History in New York State's Capital District.
Arrangement of the Collection
This collection is ordered alphabetically.
Labor; Labor union locals--United States; Albany Typographical Union No. 4 (Albany, N.Y.); Albany Typographical Union Number Four (Albany, N.Y.); New York (State); Columbia County (N.Y.); Administrative records; Correspondence; Minutes; Photographs; Pamphlets; Columbia County Typographical Union No. 896
- Address by Charles G. Alonge on Unionism, 1947 (Box 1 (Columbia County Typographical Union No. 896 Record), Folder 1)
- Annual Banquet, First, 1927 (Box 1 (Columbia County Typographical Union No. 896 Record), Folder 2)
- Annual Banquet, Fifteenth, 1951 (Box 1 (Columbia County Typographical Union No. 896 Record), Folder 3)
- Annual Banquet, 1964 (Box 1 (Columbia County Typographical Union No. 896 Record), Folder 4)
- Apprentice Record Book, 1955-1964 (Box 1 (Columbia County Typographical Union No. 896 Record), Folder 5)
- Audit Reports and Membership Statements, 1960-1964 (Box 1 (Columbia County Typographical Union No. 896 Record), Folder 6)
- Business Card and Working Card--Samples, 1945 (Box 1 (Columbia County Typographical Union No. 896 Record), Folder 7)
- Constitution and By-Laws, circa, 1945-1955 (Box 1 (Columbia County Typographical Union No. 896 Record), Folder 8)
- Contracts and Scales of Prices, Catskill Daily Mail, 1959-1960 (Box 1 (Columbia County Typographical Union No. 896 Record), Folder 9)
- Contracts and Scales of Prices, Chatham Courier Company, 1959; 1961; 1965 (Box 1 (Columbia County Typographical Union No. 896 Record), Folder 10)
- Contracts and Scales of Prices, Davis Printing Company, 1964 (Box 1 (Columbia County Typographical Union No. 896 Record), Folder 11)
- Contracts and Scales of Prices, Greene and Ulster Printing Company, 1959-1960; 1962; 1965 (Box 1 (Columbia County Typographical Union No. 896 Record), Folder 12)
- Contracts and Scales of Prices, Hudson Republican Corporation, 1937; 1939; 1941 (Box 1 (Columbia County Typographical Union No. 896 Record), Folder 13)
- Contracts and Scales of Prices, Record Printing & Publishing, 1938-1954 (Box 1 (Columbia County Typographical Union No. 896 Record), Folder 14)
- Contracts and Scales of Prices, Record Printing & Publishing, 1954-1966 (Box 1 (Columbia County Typographical Union No. 896 Record), Folder 15)
- Contracts and Scales of Prices, Stuyvesant Press, 1961 (Box 1 (Columbia County Typographical Union No. 896 Record), Folder 16)
- Correspondence, General, 1955-1956; 1955-1967 (Box 1 (Columbia County Typographical Union No. 896 Record), Folder 17)
- Correspondence, Anti-Strikebreaker Ordinance in Hudson, NY, 1964 (Box 1 (Columbia County Typographical Union No. 896 Record), Folder 18)
- Correspondence, Consolidation with Albany Typographical Union No. 4, 1963-1966 (Box 1 (Columbia County Typographical Union No. 896 Record), Folder 19)
- Correspondence, Republicans Using Non-Union Shops for Printing, 1961 (Box 1 (Columbia County Typographical Union No. 896 Record), Folder 20)
- Correspondence, Requests for Mediation, 1948-1950 (Box 1 (Columbia County Typographical Union No. 896 Record), Folder 21)
- Correspondence, Scale Negotiations, 1941 (Box 1 (Columbia County Typographical Union No. 896 Record), Folder 22)
- Correspondence, Typographical Label Fraud Investigation, 1965 (Box 1 (Columbia County Typographical Union No. 896 Record), Folder 23)
- List of Unions in the Area, 1961 (Box 1 (Columbia County Typographical Union No. 896 Record), Folder 24)
- Minutes, 1936-1940 (Box 1 (Columbia County Typographical Union No. 896 Record), Folder 25)
- Minutes, 1941-1950 (Box 2 (Columbia County Typographical Union No. 896 Record), Folder 1)
- Minutes, 1950-1959 (Box 2 (Columbia County Typographical Union No. 896 Record), Folder 2)
- Minutes, 1960-1966 (Box 2 (Columbia County Typographical Union No. 896 Record), Folder 3)
- Pamphlets from the International Typographical Union, 1949; 1964-1967 (Box 2 (Columbia County Typographical Union No. 896 Record), Folder 4)
- Permits for Use of the Typographical Union Label, 1953; 1955-1956; 1965 (Box 2 (Columbia County Typographical Union No. 896 Record), Folder 5)
- Photographs of Delegates to International Typographical Union Conventions, 1927; 1936 (Box 2 (Columbia County Typographical Union No. 896 Record), Folder 6)
- Program from Empire State Typographical Conference (hosted by Columbia County Typographical Union No. 896), 1961 (Box 2 (Columbia County Typographical Union No. 896 Record), Folder 7)
- Report on Rally for Striking Papermakers Local 479, 1950-1960 (Box 2 (Columbia County Typographical Union No. 896 Record), Folder 8)
- Reports on Condition of Finance, 1957-1965 (Box 2 (Columbia County Typographical Union No. 896 Record), Folder 9)
- Reports to New York State Department of Labor, 1959-1966 (Box 2 (Columbia County Typographical Union No. 896 Record), Folder 10)
- Reports to U.S. Department of Labor, 1959-1966 (Box 2 (Columbia County Typographical Union No. 896 Record), Folder 11)
- Seniority Lists, 1937; 1953; 1955 (Box 2 (Columbia County Typographical Union No. 896 Record), Folder 12)
- "Strike is Won!", Pamphlet of New York Typographical Union No. 6, 1963 (Box 2 (Columbia County Typographical Union No. 896 Record), Folder 13)